Okay, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov.
Today's דף daf is
ד'. Daled. Today's ד', Daled, four, and four days in the עומר.
Omer. Good way to remember one if you've forgotten the other. And
we pick up with the משנה Mishnah at the bottom of ג'
עמוד ב'. Gimmel Amud Bet. So let's just keep on, let's just
go at it. הורו בית דין וידעו שטעו וחזרו בהן. Horu Beit
Din veyadu sheta'u vechazru bahen. So בית דין Beit Din ruled and
they became aware that they made a mistake and they retracted their
ruling. בין שהביאו
כפרתן ובין שלא הביאו כפרתן. bein sheheviu kapparatam uvein shelo heviu kapparatam.
And they either have or have not brought their sacrifice. They're now
obligated in a special sacrifice. והלך היחיד ועשה על פיהם. vehalach hayachid
ve'asa al pihem. And then somebody who didn't get the message went
and continued to eat this חלב. chelev. He never heard that they
had retracted. No newspapers, right, exactly, and no radio. רבי שמעון פוטר
רבי אליעזר אומר ספק. Rabbi Shimon poter Rabbi Eliezer omer safek. Rabbi
Shimon says he's exempt from a קרבן korban because he was still
following בית דין. Beit Din. Now this gets to that interesting question
of why do you think the individual who follows is exempt from
a קרבן? korban? And remember the גמרא Gemara made a point of
saying that there's a חכמים chachamim out there, a majority position presumably,
that thinks the individual is obligated in a קרבן. korban. If בית
דין Beit Din isn't obligated, you might be blameless but you're at
the end of the day the one who does it. Okay, so
there's an opinion that even though you're blameless you bring a קרבן.
korban. Our משנה Mishnah assumes you don't. Is the reason our משנה
Mishnah assumes you don't because, and here's a good conceptual way of
looking at it to help explain this debate we're about to see,
because you're blameless. You know, you were assuming it was okay, okay,
and that's why, so it's the absence of blame. Or does it
assume that you don't because we frame what you're doing as not
so much your act, but as your sort of doing it based
on בית דין's Beit Din's ruling. You know, it's sort of an
outcome of בית דין's Beit Din's acts and so on. So a
good נפקא מינא, nafka mina, as we say, a good test case
would be this case where psychologically in your own state of mind
because you didn't get the news, you are still going on בית
דין's Beit Din's rulings. So if that's the reason you're exempt, you're
exempt here as well, which is what רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says.
But if the reason you're exempt is not because you're blameless, the
reason you're exempt is because it's not so much your act, it's
more like it's all בית דין's Beit Din's act, it's all, you
know, what they did and so on. Maybe we only say that
to the degree that their ruling is still in effect. If their
ruling is still in effect and you're operating according to it, then
it's essentially it's all their doing. Okay, once their ruling stops being
in effect, okay, even if you're blameless, it stops being seen as
you're just acting according to their ruling because you're not acting according
to, in your mind you're acting according to their ruling, but objectively
you're not. Okay, so רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says it's a ספק.
safek. It's a doubt whether in this case you're obligated in a
קרבן korban or not.
איזהו ספק? Eizehu safek? Now the משנה Mishnah continues, what would constitute
a situation of doubt? ישב לו בתוך ביתו חייב הלך למדינת הים
פטור. yashav lo betoch beito chayav halach limdinat hayam patur.
So if you're in your house, you're חייב chayav because then you
should have heard or you probably heard what בית דין Beit Din
did. If you went on a trip and you're not around, you're
פטור patur because you didn't hear. So where's the ספק? safek? You
just told me in one case you're definitely חייב chayav and in
the other case you're definitely פטור. patur. So רש"י Rashi says חייב
chayav here means you're חייב chayav an אשם תלוי. asham talui. An
אשם תלוי asham talui is the קרבן korban that I bring if
I ate a piece of meat and then I realized, oh my
god, that might have been forbidden fat. So I definitely did an
act and I don't know if that act constituted a sin that
I bring a קרבן korban for. In that case I bring a
קרבן korban called an אשם ספק, asham safek, an אשם תלוי. asham
talui. Okay,
so when it says חייב chayav here it means you're חייב chayav
an אשם תלוי. asham talui. So which is the case that we
say you have doubtfully violated, you're doubtfully obligated in a קרבן korban
and therefore you bring an אשם תלוי? asham talui? That's when you
were at home. When you were in a position that you could
have heard. But if you're on a trip and you're definitely could
not have heard, so you're totally blameless, so you're פטור. patur. Okay,
so for רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon it actually seems that רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon is not saying this fancy approach I said before. Actually
not רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer is agreeing to רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. He's saying, רבי שמעון,
Rabbi Shimon, I agree. As soon as the guy is totally blameless,
he's פטור. patur. And that's why, even though בית דין's Beit Din's
ruling stopped being in effect, and that's why if he's on a
trip, he's over in Hawaii, okay, so therefore he is פטור patur
because even though their ruling isn't in effect and he's not going
according to their ruling, their ruling has been retracted, in his mind
he is and his state of being blameless and not knowing is
enough to exempt him. What I don't know is if he's at
home. If he's at home and on the one hand he actually
has not heard, so therefore you should say he's blameless. On the
other hand, maybe he should ask around. Maybe he, you know, maybe
he doesn't get out enough, maybe, you know, there's the ability for
him to hear. So how much do we say it was possible
for him to hear makes him considered not totally blameless? That he
says I don't know. And therefore in that case I say he
has to bring an אשם תלוי asham talui because he's ספק. safek.
it could be he's not really blameless in that situation. Okay, so
everybody agrees to the principle that if you're even though their ruling
is over, if you in if you are actually blameless, you don't
bring a קרבן korban and the point that ר' אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
just says is I just think if he's at home, even if
he hasn't heard, he's not necessarily totally blameless cause maybe he could
have heard and therefore he's a ספק safek and he brings an
אשם תלוי. asham taloy. Yes.
So this idea of if he's away on a trip, doesn't that
contradict the concept that you were expressing that even if because it's
no longer...
Yeah, that's what I said. I was framing it as it's possible
to say it's not about being blameless, but what we see from
the fact that ר' אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer concedes to the case of
being away on a trip, that he agrees in principle to the
approach of ר' שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, that it is really about being
blameless. This other approach I said will come up in the גמרא.
Gemara. Okay, but it seems like here they're all just disagreeing on
the principle and they're just disagreeing on the application. Do we assign
a status of blamelessness to the guy who remains at home? Okay,
now,
אמר ר' עקיבא Amar Rabbi Akiva מודה אני בזה שהוא קרוב לפטור
מן החובה. Modeh ani bazeh shehu karov liftoor min hachovah. I agree
to the guy who's going on a trip that it makes more
sense that he's completely exempt. אמר לו בן עזאי Amar lo Ben
Azzai מה שנה זה מן היושב בביתו? Mah shnah zeh min hayoshev
beiveito? What's the difference? I mean the answer seems so obvious. So
ר' עקיבא Rabbi Akiva responds שהיושב בביתו אפשר היה לו שישמע ולא
היה לו אפשר וזה לא היה לו אפשר שישמע. Shehayoshev beiveito efshar
hayah lo sheyishma velo hayah lo efshar vezeh lo hayah lo efshar
sheyishma. In both cases, in one case when he's away, he is
truly blameless, there was no ability for him to have heard the
message, whereas at home maybe he could have heard and therefore he's
not in a totally blameless situation. Okay, now we move on to
a completely different point. So that's ending the previous משנה mishna that
it's all that the question about when does the individual who follows
בית דין beis din exempt. Now we get to when is the
בית דין beis din חייב. chayav. So obviously it's in a case
when the majority of the ציבור tzibur listens to them, but before
we get to people listening to them, we're going to deal with
the substance of the ruling. הורו לבטל מקצת ולקיים מקצת הרי אלו
חייבין. Horu levatel miktzas ulekayem miktzas harei eilu chayavin. If their ruling
was to get rid of a part of a מצוה mitzvah but
to keep the rest of it, that's the only case in which
they're חייב chayav where they didn't make a ruling to completely sort
of say a whole מצוה mitzvah doesn't apply all together. But where
they where they had a ruling about a details and they got
the details wrong and as a result of the details, right, they're
sort of saying this detail, you know, isn't really a you know
doesn't apply in this case, they actually caused somebody to sin. Okay
now, כיצד? keitzad? אמרו יש נדה בתורה אבל הבא על שומרת יום
כנגד יום פטור. Amru yesh niddah batorah aval haba al shomeres yom
keneged yom patur. If they said we agree to the concept of
נדה niddah in the תורה, Torah, a woman who gets her period,
but if a woman who's a שומרת יום כנגד יום shomeres yom
keneged yom stains in the middle or bleeds in the middle of
her cycle, then that's not a problem and then if a man
has sex with such a woman he they're exempt. Okay, so that's
keeping the general category but getting a certain detail wrong or not
even such a tiny detail.
יש שבת בתורה המוציא מרשות היחיד לרשות הרבים פטור. Yesh shabbos batorah
hamozi mereshus hayachid lereshus harabim patur. There is a concept of שבת,
shabbos, but there's no הלכה halachah of הוצאה hotzaah of carrying. יש
עבודת כוכבים בתורה אבל המשתחוה פטור. Yesh avodas kochavim batorah aval hamishtachaveh
patur.
There's a prohibition of worshipping idols but prostration is not a sufficient
act of worship. So in those cases הרי אלו חייבין, harei eilu
chayavin, they're חייב. chayav. שנאמר ונעלם דבר. Shene'emar vena'alam davar. An aspect
gets hidden from them. דבר ולא כל הגוף Davar velo kol haguf
not the entire body of law. Okay so we'll see more about
this in the גמרא. Gemara. That's a completely separate point. Let's start
with this issue about when the individual who follows בית דין beis
din is פטור patur or not. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב Amar
Rav Yehudah Amar Rav מאי טעמיה דר' שמעון? Mai ta'amei deRabbi Shimon?
What's the reason of ר' שמעון Rabbi Shimon who says that you're
exempt in all cases even if you're at home? הואיל וברשות בית
דין הוא עושה. Ho'il ubireshus beis din hu oseh. Since he's operating
with the license of the court. The irony is it's no longer
the license of the court because the court retracted the ruling but
in his mind it is. ואיכא דאמרי Ve'ika de'amri אמר רב יהודה
אמר רב Amar Rav Yehudah Amar Rav אמר ר' שמעון Amar Rabbi
Shimon כל הוראה שיצאה ברוב ציבור kol hora'ah sheyatzah berov tzibur any
ruling that has been disseminated through the majority of the community יחיד
העושה אותה פטור yachid ha'oseh osah patur the individual who follows this
is exempt לפי שלא ניתנה הוראה אלא להבחין בין שוגג למזיד. Lefi
shelo nitenah hora'ah ela lehavchin bein shogeg lemeizid. It's a funny phrase.
Normally we hear the phrase לא ניתנה התראה אלא להבחין בין שוגג
למזיד. Lo nitenah hatra'ah ela lehavchin bein shogeg lemeizid. When they warn
a person before doing a sin, the whole purpose is the purpose
to formalize the act sometimes as an act of rebellion or is
the purpose just to determine his state of mind? Here it says
the same thing about הוראה hora'ah the ruling of the court okay
that the only purpose of the ruling of the court was to
determine your state of mind. What does that mean? So I think
it's very clear what it means. I think it means that in
order to exempt you it's really just a question of what was
your state of mind. It's not a question of objectively are you
following the ruling of בית דין beis din because once they retracted
you are no longer objectively following their ruling. Their ruling has been
retracted. But if the purpose the reason you're exempt in the first
משנה mishna was because of your state of mind not because of
the objective reality of following בית דין beis din but because you
had legitimately believed that this was what they had ruled and therefore
you were blameless so he says that's just as true now even
after they retracted themselves. That doesn't
change. So that's רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon's approach. It all goes to
the question of blamelessness and state of mind. מיתבי, Meisvei, now I'll
ask you on this. פר העלם דבר של ציבור ושעירי עבודת כוכבים,
Par Helam Davar Shel Tzibbur Ve'Seirei Avodas Kochavim, so when you have
to go ahead and buy these קרבנות, Korbanos, the פר העלם דבר
של ציבור, Par Helam Davar Shel Tzibbur, that's our case where they
bring the special קרבן, Korban, which is an ox, and they bring
it because, you know, the ציבור, Tzibbur, something was hidden from the
whole congregation, meaning a wrong ruling of בית דין Beis Din that
everybody followed. Okay, that's our case. And שעירי עבודת כוכבים Seirei Avodas
Kochavim is a parallel case, but the ruling related to עבודת כוכבים
Avodas Kochavim and therefore it was a goat. Okay, and these are
communal sacrifices. Who, where would the money come from to buy these
sacrifices that would be brought by the court? So בתחילה גובין להן
דברי רבי שמעון. Betchila Govin Lahen Divrei Rebbi Shimon. רבי שמעון Rebbi
Shimon says you do a new collection for this money. Okay, you
go out and you tax everybody ten cents in order from the
entire per person from the entire population so you get the money
to buy this cow or whatever it is. It's funny, like imagine
a whole population, how much does each person have to give? But
okay, you do a special collection in order to raise the money
for these sacrifices. רבי יהודה אומר מתרומת הלשכה הן באין. Rebbi Yehuda
Omer Mi'Trumas HaLishka Hen Ba'in. No, they come from the communal funds
that are usually used to bring the daily sacrifices. Okay,
now, אמאי, Amai, now, כיון דגבי להו, Keivan D'Gavi Lehu, now according
to you, now if it's all about state of mind according to
רבי שמעון, Rebbi Shimon, we've got a problem. Because since רבי שמעון
Rebbi Shimon says you would do a special tax collection, then everybody
should know that בית דין Beis Din changed their ruling, okay, because
you're collecting the money for this קרבן. Korban. Now you could say
just because they realized and retracted doesn't mean that they brought the
קרבן Korban yet. But remember the משנה Mishnah says even after they
brought the קרבן. Korban. The משנה Mishnah says whether they brought or
didn't bring the קרבן, Korban, so רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon would say
an individual is פטור Patur even after בית דין Beis Din has
brought the קרבן. Korban. Just appreciate that, right? Not only did they
retract, they actually have like closed off the whole case. They retracted,
they acknowledged, they brought a קרבן. Korban. You didn't get the message
and you're still operating based on that old information and you're still
פטור. Patur. So that really shows for רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon how
much it's an issue of state of mind. But the גמרא Gemara
says I don't get it, if they already brought the קרבן, Korban,
then you must have heard, because we did, according to רבי שמעון,
Rebbi Shimon, we did a special collection of funds for this קרבן.
Korban. Okay, so אמאי, Amai, כיון דגבי להו, Keivan D'Gavi Lehu, since
they raised the funds, הויא
להו הודעה, Havei Lehu Hoda'ah, he should have found out about it.
So איבעית אימא, Iba'is Eima, כגון שגבו סתם. Kegon She'Gavu Stam. One
possibility
is they just sent out a message, we need to collect money
for something. We're not telling you why. Okay? Special fundraising campaign, trust
us we'll use the money for a good thing. So okay, איבעית
אימא, Iba'is Eima, if you want, כגון דלא הוה במתא. Kegon De'Lo
Hava B'Masa. Maybe he was away when they actually were collecting the
funds. Okay, he's home now.
That's like the other case.
That's like the other case, but here it's just away when they
were collecting the funds, not away when you, you know, for the
whole period. ואיבעית אימא, V'Iba'is Eima, if you want I could tell
you, רב גידל תנא סבר. Rav Giddal Tanna Savar. רב Rav who
gave this explanation of the משנה, Mishnah, he held like the other
תנא. Tanna. דתניא איפכא בתחילה גובין להן דברי רבי יהודה. Detanya Ipcha
Betchila Govin Lahen Divrei Rebbi Yehuda. רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda is the
one who says you do a special
collection. ורבי שמעון אומר מתרומת הלשכה הן באין. VeRebbi Shimon Omer Mi'Trumas
HaLishka Hen Ba'in. Okay, מתרומת הלשכה, Mi'Trumas HaLishka, but anyway, but this
is a nice way of underscoring the phrase לא ניתנה הוראה אלא
להבחין בין שוגג למזיד Lo Nitna Hora'ah Ela L'Havchin Bein Shogeg L'Mezid
that according to him, it's a totally a question of state of
mind. Now תני, Tani, we have a ברייתא. Braisa. רבי מאיר מחייב.
Rebbi Meir Mechayev. רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir actually says that you're חייב.
Chayav. So that actually is interesting, we haven't seen this before. רבי
מאיר Rebbi Meir says that you're חייב Chayav straight, not a ספק.
Safek. Okay, even though once בית דין Beis Din retracted, you bring
your personal קרבן. Korban. So רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir might be this
position that I was mentioning before. רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir might be
saying, I don't care that you're blameless. I don't care if you
were במדינת הים, B'Medinas HaYam, I don't care. Since objectively they retracted,
you no longer are operating with their license and therefore even though
you're blameless, a sin was done, you did it, you have to
bring it. If you're just seen as an extension of them operating
with their license, maybe everybody could be off the hook. Okay, but
once that objective reality has stopped and you're the one who did
it, you bring the קרבן. Korban. That's what even though your state
of mind, whatever, you're blameless. That's רבי מאיר. Rebbi Meir. רבי שמעון
פוטר. Rebbi Shimon Poter. רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon we know says you're
פטור Patur and he says it's totally about state of mind. רבי
אליעזר אומר ספק. Rebbi Eliezer Omer Safek. רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer is
ספק, Safek, that we've seen. And the way the משנה Mishnah explains
the ספק, Safek, it's because he doesn't know, your conscious state of
mind is that, you know, you think you're okay, but the actual
state of mind is that you're blameless, whatever, you think you're operating
with license, but in theory you could know better. So are we
prepared to put you in that same blameless category? That's רבי אליעזר.
Rebbi Eliezer. And now we have yet a fourth position other than
רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir who says straight out you're
חייב. Chayav. סומכוס אמרו משום סומכוס אמרו תלוי. Sumchus Amru Mi'Shum Sumchus
Amru Taluy. סומכוס Sumchus says it is suspended. Okay, so what does
suspended mean? So suspended sounds like אשם תלוי, Asham Taluy, but the
גמרא Gemara is going to say it actually means you don't bring
a קרבן Korban because we don't know, like it's a different type
of a ספק Safek than רבי אליעזר. Rebbi Eliezer. We'll take a
look about what this means in a moment. אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar
Rabbi Yochanan, so what does that mean? אשם תלוי איכא בינייהו. Asham
Talui ika beineihu. The debate is whether you bring an אשם תלוי.
Asham Talui. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer thinks that it's a standard case
of doubt, like you don't know if you ate the טרפה, treifah,
and you bring an אשם תלוי. Asham Talui. And סומכוס Sumchos says
I don't know if there's enough basis to bring anything. Okay, yes,
there's a doubt here, but it's a different type of a doubt.
So what's the difference? So let's take a look. אמר רב זירא,
Amar Rav Zeira, משל דרבי אליעזר למה הדבר דומה: mashal deRabbi Eliezer
lema davar domeh: what can רבי אליעזר'ס Rabbi Eliezer's case be compared
to?
לאדם שאכל ספק חלב ספק שומן. leadom she'achal safek chelev safek shuman.
A person ate a piece of meat and he didn't know was
it kosher fat or treif fat. The reason they do fat and
they don't say something like נבלה neveilah is because נבלה neveilah you
don't bring a קרבן korban for it, it has to be something
that is possible כרת. kareis. You could say somebody ate a pita
and didn't know if it was Sefardi מצה matzah or if it
was real חמץ. chametz. Okay, so ונודע לו, venoda lo, and then
he realized that he might have done an עבירה, aveirah, שמביא אשם
תלוי, shemeivi asham talui, he brings an אשם תלוי. asham talui. Okay,
because why? Because this is a similar thing. In one case you
don't know if you had the right piece of meat to be
חייב. chayav. In this case you don't know if you had the
right frame of mind to be חייב. chayav. Do you have sufficient
blamelessness? Okay, your actual state of mind is you think you're operating
for בית דין. Beis Din. Does that count as your like as
one what we sort of define as your like you know legal
from a הלכה halachic point of view your state of mind? Because
in the end of the day maybe there's a little willful ignorance
here, maybe you know you could know and therefore maybe you're not
blameless, okay. So let's take a look. דלא מיבעיא, delo miba'ei, so
we don't know if you have the right conditions for חיוב, chiyuv,
and therefore it's like we don't know if you didn't have the
right piece of meat to be obligated. We don't know if you
have the right state of mind to be obligated. דלא מיבעיא למאן
דאמר ציבור מייתו, delo miba'ei leman de'amar tzibur meivu, it now it
goes without saying. So remember he this position says you have to
you're חייב chayav a קרבן אשם תלוי. korban asham talui. We don't
know if you're חייב חטאת chayav chatas but there's enough of a
reason to say that you did a sin that you have to
bring an אשם תלוי. asham talui. So the fact that you're obligated
some form of a קרבן korban it goes without that there might
be there's enough basis to think you sinned. It goes without that
according to the one that says it's the community that brings the
קרבן, korban, דמפרסמא מילתא. demifarsma milsa. If the if when בית דין
Beis Din made a wrong ruling the community brings the קרבן korban
now it's going to be much more public right because now the
community has to raise the money and bring a קרבן korban and
whatever. It's going to be much more public what they did and
then certainly you should have known. אלא
אפילו למאן דאמר בית דין מייתי ella afilu leman de'amar Beis Din
meivi even if it's the בית דין Beis Din that brings the
קרבן korban דלא מפרסמא מילתא delo mifarsma milsa it has not been
so publicized
nevertheless we could say you know what it's very nice that you're
ignorant but ignorance of the law or ignorance of relevant facts is
no excuse and we're still going to say דהוה שאיל הוה אמרינן
ליה dehavei sho'el hava amrinan leh if you would have asked people
would have told you. So the same way for example if I
ate this forbidden piece of meat you know you could have or
we don't know if it was forbidden but you could have asked
and found out and so on and there's an objective reality that
I might have eaten treif meat. So here too there's an objective
you could have found out you know you could have determined that
and there's an objective reality that you were operating like you know
without the awareness of בית without the license of בית דין Beis
Din and you know you might
the your state of mind might not be considered a blameless state
of mind okay it might not be considered that you really were
acting because you were relying on them. In your subjective mindset you
were relying on them but it could be that you know because
you could have asked around and realized you didn't have a right
to be and we're not really prepared to define it as such.
Okay so therefore because of those doubts it's an you're not going
to bring a חטאת chatas but you will bring an אשם תלוי.
asham talui.
That's that's רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. Now we
already dealt with רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer now we're going to look
at the new position of רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. אמר רבי יוסי
בר אבין ואי תימא רבי יוסי בר זבידא Amar Rabbi Yose bar
Avin ve'iseima Rabbi Yose bar Zvida משל דסומכוס למה הדבר דומה. mashal
deSumchos lema davar domeh. סומכוס Sumchos is the new interesting position. What
can that be compared to?
לאדם שהביא כפרתו בין השמשות. leadom sheheivi kaparato bein hashmashot. Somebody brought
his sacrifice he knew he was obligated in a sacrifice and he
brought it right at the end of the day right when it
was right at that moment right after sunset.
ספק מבעוד יום נתכפר לו ספק משיחשיכה נתכפר לו. safek mibod yom
nitkapeir lo safek mishehachishah nitkapeir lo. We don't know if it was
brought while it was still day or if it was brought when
it was halachically night because it was brought during this gray zone.
Okay so in that case שאין מביא אשם תלוי she'ein meivi asham
talui that in that case you don't bring a קרבן. korban. And
the fact that you don't bring a קרבן korban means even in
a case where I might think it should be more obvious you
should bring a קרבן. korban. דלא מיבעיא למאן דאמר בית דין מייתי
דלא מפרסמא מילתא. delo miba'ei leman de'amar Beis Din meivi delo farsma
milsa. It goes without saying according to the position that says בית
דין beis din. bring that it's not so public so that's more
obvious you don't bring a קרבן korban because it was not you
couldn't have known so easily. אלא אפילו למאן דאמר ציבור מייתו דמפרסמא
מילתא. ella afilu leman de'amar tzibur meivu demifarsma milsa. Even if the
ציבור tzibur brings and it was more public and I could say
maybe you more should have known more reason to say you're obligated
at least
an אשם תלוי asham talui okay והוה אמרינן ליה דהכא בספק מבעוד
יום ספק משיחשיכה vehava amrinan leh de'hacha besafek mibod yom safek mishehachishah
so
some folks they got this next line because Nevertheless, we say ישאל
לא אשכח איניש דמשיילי. ishal lo askach inish dumeshailei. It's still like
this question of בין השמשות bein hashmashos because had he asked then
he might not have found somebody to tell him. Now that last
line wasn't so clear but let me tell you what I think
is really being said here is the following is that actually it's
a great analogy. The two analogies are great, okay? The first analogy
is you don't know if you ate the טרייף treif piece of
meat, okay, and you bring an אשם תלוי. asham talui. Well that's
like I don't know if you had what we'd be considered a
sufficient you know you're sufficiently blameworthy or to say it another way
whether your state of mind could sufficiently be said to be relying
on בית דין. beis din Yes that's true that was in your
consciousness but because you know you could have asked and found out
more information I'm not sure I'm willing to attribute that to be
how to define your subjective act and how to define your state
of mind. So that's sort of like I don't know if I
have the criteria here to make you obligated and therefore depends on
do we assess this as though you are blameless or blameworthy, do
we assess this as though you were in your state of in
your in your subjective perspective you were relying on בית דין beis
din? or not relying on בית דין? beis din So since I
don't know it's like I don't know whether the piece of meat
was כשר kosher or טרייף treif and you bring an אשם תלוי.
asham talui. That's רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. סומכוס, Sumchus, the בין השמשות
bein hashmashos example is great. Why is it great? Well it depends
what you think about בין השמשות bein hashmashos but if you think
that בין השמשות bein hashmashos what it is is that
it's
not just a question of technically did it happen during the day
or not during the day, it's a period of objective ספק. safek.
This is the way רב Rav Soloveitchik explains it. I mean according
to what I'm saying the גמרא Gemara should have had a better
analogy. The better analogy should have been I did מלאכה melacha on
ערב שבת erev Shabbos right right at בין השמשות. bein hashmashos. Okay?
That would have been a better analogy. And there you could say
it's not just a question of so that's actually a discussion in
the גמרא Gemara do you bring an אשם תלוי asham talui or
not whatever so maybe anyway but my point is is that what
I think סומכוס Sumchus is saying is סומכוס Sumchus is saying like
for me the ספק safek is not the facts. For me the
ספק safek is the law. What does that mean the ספק safek
is the law? Because it depends which lens you put on it.
If you put on a רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir lens and remember
סומכוס Sumchus is a student of רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, so רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir says I don't care that you're blameless. Objectively בית
דין beis din's had retracted the ruling and you were no longer
going according to בית דין's beis din's ruling. So from a רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir lens you're totally חייב chayav because he does the
objective reality of whether you're following בית דין's beis din rulings. Okay?
From a רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon lens he goes by your state
of mind and by your state of mind you're following בית דין
beis din, ruling and you're totally פטור. patur. So I actually think
that the problem here is is if you would it's not a
question of not knowing the facts. If you don't know the facts
well enough you bring an אשם תלוי asham talui if the facts
might have been such. Here the problem is is as it were
like you know the two the two frameworks contradict.
Objectively you're not following בית דין, beis din. but your frame of
mind is that you are following בית דין. beis din And that
puts you exactly between the situation the legal status of being חייב
chayav and the legal status of being פטור patur and it's not
a question of the facts, it's a question that the law itself
sort of leads to you know two different ways of framing it.
I guess he can't choose which way but maybe he says both
are true, okay? And therefore since you can't since since there's like
a this is a middle state therefore it's not enough to be
חייב chayav in a קרבן. korban. All right? I'm trying to think
what another good example would be about a middle state you know.
There's basically two steps. One would be to take from רבי אליעזר'ס
Rabbi Eliezer's to
say the last sentence that
there's no real question of could you have known. Right? He excludes
that by saying that's not relevant because we don't expect that of
anyone. Nonetheless comes a second layer I think which is
what you were trying to say.
Right that's what I'm trying to say. Right meaning exactly.
Right that's a good point. Right because from a רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer perspective once you have the two lenses you could say you're
חייב chayav both ways. From רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir you're definitely חייב
chayav and from a רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer perspective you know
maybe you could have known. Right? So that would you're right so
if you had but if you say from a רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer perspective we don't expect you to ask around we don't expect
you I concede that in the guy's mindset he's totally blameless and
that's a legitimate mindset. I'm just saying that there's two contradictory ways
of looking at this and therefore you're caught in this middle position.
That's the way I'd like to read it. Okay anyway so there
you go three different two fundamentally different models. A model of whether
objectively you're following בית דין Beis Din רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir or
a model of subjectively whether you're you know whether you're listening to
them and whether you're blameless. And within that subjective model you have
three possibilities. We always consider you blameless. Well two. We always consider
you blameless we don't know whether to consider you blameless or not
so you bring an אשם תלוי asham talui and then you have
this interesting position of סומכוס Sumchus which I actually see he's saying
I don't know how to pick between the two different models. Okay
so let's continue in the גמרא. Gemara. אמר ליה בן עזאי מה
שנא היושב שפיר קאמר ליה רבי עקיבא Amar leh Ben Azzai mai
shna hayoshev shapir kamlei Rabbi Akiva isn't רבי עקיבא'ס Rabbi Akiva's answer
obvious that the guy
who The difference is
is that you're packing and you're on your way to the airport
and that's when בית דין Beis Din comes out with their announcement.
Okay, ובין עזאי חייב דהא בביתיה איתיה. u'ven Azzai chayav de-ha be-veiseih
isei. You're still at home, you're just waiting for the Uber to
arrive, but you could still be hearing about things, okay? And therefore
he says I don't get why you're exempt. רבי עקיבא פוטר דהחזיק
בדרך Rabbi Akiva potir de-hichzik b'derech and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says
even at that stage you're exempt because you're too busy and you're
on your way getting ready for your trip. Alright. Moving on. So
that's the end of our first discussion which is following the ruling
of בית דין Beis Din that the individual is exempt and as
I said I think this brings out very nicely two different ways
of understanding why the individual is exempt and not to forget that
there's the another position which is that the individual is חייב chayav
even if בית דין's beit din ruling is still in effect because
at the end of the day somebody's got to bring a קרבן.
korban. Okay. Now we get to the substance of the ruling. הורו
בית דין לעקור את כל הגוף. Horu Beis Din la'akor es kol
ha-guf. תנו
רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. ונעלם דבר ולא שתעקר מצוה כולה. V'ne'elam davar v'lo
she-te'aker mitzvah kullah. A matter was hidden and not the entire body
of law. כיצד? Keitzad? אמרו אין נדה בתורה אין שבת בתורה אין
עבודת כוכבים בתורה. Amru ein niddah ba-Torah ein Shabbos ba-Torah ein avodas
kochavim ba-Torah. If they say there's no נדה niddah or שבת Shabbos
or עבודת כוכבים. avodas kochavim. Interesting by the way that he picks
those three if you think about it. Like you know like three
of like probably the most major things, like the one that's missing
is sort of like כשרות kashrus example, okay? But where we would
say שבת, Shabbos, כשרות, kashrus, and טהרת המשפחה, taharas ha-mishpachah, and like
עבודה זרה avodah zarah is your basic, you know, obviously the basic
God part about the whole thing. So alright. יכול יהיו חייבין. Yachol
yihiyu chayavin. Maybe they'd be חייב chayav if they wiped away a
whole thing? תלמוד לומר ונעלם דבר ולא שתעקר מצוה כולה. Talmud lomar
v'ne'elam davar v'lo she-te'aker mitzvah kullah. No, it has to be a
matter, not the entire thing. הרי אלו פטורין. Harei elu peturin. Okay.
אבל אמרו יש נדה בתורה אבל הבא על שומרת יום כנגד יום
פטור יש שבת בתורה אבל המוציא מרשות היחיד לרשות הרבים פטור יש
עבודת כוכבים בתורה אבל המשתחוה פטור. Aval amru yesh niddah ba-Torah aval
ha-ba al shomeres yom k'neged yom patur yesh Shabbos ba-Torah aval ha-motzi
me-reshus ha-yachid l'reshus ha-rabim patur yesh avodas kochavim ba-Torah aval ha-mishtachaveh patur.
If they said yes these categories exist but certain details you're exempt
for which is counterfactual. They said you're exempt for carrying on שבת,
Shabbos, you're exempt for this case of mid-period staining, you're exempt from
bowing down to עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. יכול יהיו פטורין. Yachol yihiyu
peturin. Maybe they'd be פטור? patur? תלמוד לומר ונעלם דבר ולא כל
הגוף. Talmud lomar v'ne'elam davar v'lo kol ha-guf. A matter not the
whole thing. So אמר מר. amar mar. יכול יהיו פטורין. Yachol yihiyu
peturin. I don't get it. After you made the first statement that
you're exempt when you make a mistake about a whole body of
law, what do you mean in the second part of this ברייתא,
Braisa, maybe if you were if you got one matter wrong maybe
you'd be exempt. וכי במקצת מצוה ביטול מקצת פטורין? V'chi be-miktzas mitzvah
bittul miktzas peturin? If how could it be that you could be
exempt in in getting part of it wrong? ובביטול כל הגוף פטורין?
U-v'vittul kol ha-guf peturin? After you've already said that getting the whole
thing wrong you're exempt. So במה חייבין? be-mah chayavin? What are you
left to be חייב chayav for? So תנא הכי קא קשיא ליה.
Tana hachi ka kashya leh. This is what was bothering the תנא.
Tana. אימא
דבר כולה מילתא משמע. Eima davar kullah milsa mashma. After saying ונעלם
דבר v'ne'elam davar means
a
detail, the תנא Tana is going back and questioning his own ruling
and he's saying one minute, how do I know that דבר davar
means a detail? Maybe דבר davar means the whole matter? Okay. תלמוד
לומר ונעלם דבר. Talmud lomar v'ne'elam davar. So then it asks again
maybe that's not true, maybe it's the opposite, maybe the whole matter
is when you're חייב chayav and a detail is when you're פטור.
patur. So then therefore it says ונעלם דבר v'ne'elam davar shows you
that we're talking about a detail. Now how does it show you
we're talking about a detail? מאי משמע? Mai mashma? Where does you
get? If דבר davar could mean the whole thing, where do you
get the idea that we're talking about a detail? How do you
prove it? אמר עולא קרי ביה ונעלם מדבר. Amar Ulla kari beih
v'ne'elam mi-davar. Like there's a דגש dagesh in the מ. mem. You
repeat the מ. mem. Okay.
ונעלם מדבר. v'ne'elam mi-davar. Okay. So therefore you're it's hidden from you
an aspect of the matter. Even if the word דבר davar means
the whole thing you use the מ mem from the end of
ונעלם v'ne'elam to mean a detail of the matter is hidden from
you. Okay. חזקיה
אמר אמר קרא ועשו אחת מכל מצות. Chizkiyahu amar amar kra v'asu
achas mi-kol mitzvos. So he says actually not a פסוק pasuk quoted
in the ברייתא. Braisa. At at the end of it it says
a matter is hidden and the people go and do one of
the מצוות mitzvos that they're not supposed to do. Okay. מכל מצות.
mi-kol mitzvos. From the מצוות. mitzvos. ולא כל מצות. v'lo kol mitzvos.
And not the entire מצוה. mitzvah. So the גמרא Gemara says one
minute, מצות mitzvos תרתי משמע. tarti mashma. מצות mitzvos is plural. So
from some of the מצוות mitzvos could mean a whole מצוה, mitzvah,
right? You wanted it to say from a מצוה. mitzvah. They sinned
from an aspect of a מצוה. mitzvah. It just said מכל מצות
mi-kol mitzvos not מכל מצוה. mi-kol mitzvah. So אמר רב נחמן בר
יצחק. Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak. מצות כתיב. mitzvas ksiv. You could
read it as מצות. mitzvas. ועשו אחת
מכל מצות. v'asu achas mi-kol mitzvas. From the entirety one thing wrong
out of a whole מצוה, mitzvah, not out of all of the
מצוות. mitzvos. Okay. רב אשי אמר יליף דבר דבר מזקן ממרא. Rav
Ashi amar yalif davar davar mi-zaken mamre. The way they knew a
partial thing is from a זקן ממרא zaken mamre and this is
an important parallel whether or not it's the basis, okay? Because this
actually goes to what constitutes הוראה. hora'ah. Part of the reason if
they rule an entire thing doesn't exist is because that's not considered
הוראה. hora'ah. Like that's just considered like that is so off base
it doesn't it's not even like a you know it's I don't
know what it is, it's like they were you know it's like
they were talking about the sports scores or something. It's not close
enough, it's not in the category enough to be considered to be
a a ruling that was wrong. It was just like, it's sort
of like what the גמרא Gemara talks about the difference between like
טועה בשיקול הדעת to'eh bishikul hadaat and טועה בדבר משנה. to'eh bidvar
mishna. If you make a mistake against something that's an explicit law,
so how much is that really considered a הוראה hora'ah all together?
Right? That might not even require retraction, that might not even constitute
a הוראה. hora'ah. Okay, so anyway, so the same is true about
a זקן ממרא. Zaken Mamre. If somebody positions themselves as a competing
authority to the court and the הלכה halacha is that then they're
going to get executed if they keep on acting on it. What
type of a ruling does this person give? If this person gives
a ruling that's totally off-base, so it's so therefore it's not really
considered a ruling, so he's really not positioning himself as a competing
authority. If he goes around and starts teaching there's no such thing
as שבת Shabbos in the תורה, Torah, he might be מכשיל makhshil
people in חילול שבת, chilul Shabbos, he's causing people to sin, but
he's not doing something that's considered to be a competing ruling against
the court. That's not a ruling. Okay, so it's the same true
that's here when the court is חייב chayav for their mistaken ruling.
It has to be close enough to be considered to be a
ruling but a wrong ruling. And the same is true by זקן
ממרא. Zaken Mamre. Okay, because it says,
דכתיב בזקן ממרא, dechsiv beZaken Mamre, it says by the זקן ממרא,
Zaken Mamre, כי יפלא ממך דבר, ki yipale mimcha davar, when a
matter is hidden. So again there's that דבר. davar. לא תסור מן
הדבר אשר יגידו לך ימין ושמאל. Lo sasur min hadavar asher yagidu
lecha yamin u'smol. So מאי ממרי מן הדבר, mai mamri min hadavar,
מן הדבר min hadavar is again clear from an aspect of the
matter and לא כל דבר, lo kol davar, not that he's going
against an entire body of law. אף פה הוראת דבר ולא כל
הגוף. Af po hora'at davar velo kol haguf. Here too. אמר רב
יהודה אמר שמואל. Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel. Fine. So now whatever
the source is, we know the source. But it's important to put
it in parallel with זקן ממרא. Zaken Mamre.
Say it's the רב אשי. Rav Ashi. I think this is a
common theme that רב אשי Rav Ashi feels free to offer his
own לימודים. limudim.
That's interesting. But here a couple of אמוראים Amoraim are offering their
own לימודים, limudim, but you might be true about רב אשי Rav
Ashi in general. Okay. Now, אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל אין בית
דין חייבין עד שיורו בדבר שאין הצדוקים מודים בו. amar Rav Yehuda
amar Shmuel ein beit din chayavin ad sheyoru bedavar she'ein hatzedukim modim
bo. So here's another way of sort of saying that it has
to be close enough to be considered a real ruling, meaning it's
something that actually you could understand that people could that is not
black and white. Okay, so similar to like טועה בדבר משנה. to'eh
bidvar mishna. If it's something that even the Sadducees would say is
wrong, you know, then בית דין beit din is so off-base that
it's not even a ruling. Okay, so it has to be something
that there's ambiguity and they come down on one way. But if
it's something that was black and white in the פסוקים, psukim, so
black and white that even the Sadducees would say that's the law,
and they rule against it, then that's, you know, then ironically or
whatever, I don't know, then they're totally פטור pattur because they're totally
off-base. Okay. מאי טעמא זיל קרי בי רב הוא. Mai ta'ama? Zil
krei bei rav hu. Just go ask in חדר cheder and the
kids will tell you that the בית דין beit din got it
wrong. So it's not even it's not close enough to be a
ruling. Okay. So תנן יש נדה בתורה אבל הבא על שומרת יום
כנגד יום פטור. tenan yesh nidda baTorah aval habah al shomeres yom
kineged yom pattur. Let's look at the cases in the משנה. mishna.
One example is that they say that you're exempt if the בית
דין beit din rules that a man who or a woman and
a woman who have intercourse after the woman bled mid-cycle, okay, is
exempt. ואמאי שומרת יום כנגד יום הכתיב, Ve'amai? Shomeres yom kineged yom
haksiv, it's in the פסוק. pasuk. It says וספרה לה, vesafra lah,
מלמד שסופרת אחד לאחד. melamed shesoferes echad l'echad. So it says that
if a woman has, you know, she counts her days if she
bleeds mid-cycle. So it means that for every one day of bleeding,
or if she bleeds one or two days, she counts one day
of not bleeding. Now the irony of course is מלמד שסופרת אחד
לאחד melamed shesoferes echad l'echad is a rabbinic interpretation of that verse.
The simple reading of the verse is that if a woman bleeds
multiple days mid-cycle, she becomes a נדה... niddah... she becomes a זבה,
zavah, okay. It says כי יזוב זוב דמה בלא עת נדתה או
כי תזוב על נדתה, ki yazuv zav damah belo eis niddasah o
ki yazuv al niddasah, whatever, ימים רבים, yamim rabim, I'm forgetting the
פסוק. pasuk. But anyway, it says ימים רבים. yamim rabim. It says
she bleeds many days. The rabbis just go and read it to
say oh, if it's only one or two days, then she's טמא
tamei for one day afterwards. Okay, so somehow I don't have no
idea why the גמרא Gemara thinks that this is explicit in the
verse. It's totally a rabbinic read of the verse. But it claims
that it's explicit. And even the Sadducees would agree. And therefore, how
could this be what you call something that, you know, based on
your position, how could this be something בית דין would be חייב
chayav for? Okay. דאמרי, De'amri, so here the answer is fine. So
they don't say it's totally מותר. muttar. There the Sadducees would agree
that it's אסור. assur. But what they say is דאמרי העראה שריה
גמר ביאה הוא דאסירה. de'amri ha'ara sharya, gmar biah hu de'asira. The
only thing that's forbidden is when you do a full penetration, when
the shaft enters fully in, but if it's העראה, ha'ara, just the
crown penetrated, that would be exempt. Okay, so that's what they say.
That's not explicit. So the גמרא Gemara says, no, הא נמי כתיב,
ha nami ksiv, that's also explicit. את מקורה הערה, Es mekora he'erah,
that he revealed her source. Meaning, so that word הערה he'erah is
read to be just partial penetration of the מקור, makor, of the
vagina. So therefore that is explicit. It's very funny what the גמרא
Gemara thinks is explicit in the פסוקים. psukim. Anyway, דאמרי כדרכה אסירה
שלא כדרכה שריה. de'amri kedarka asira shelo kedarka sharya. No, fine. What
their ruling is is that it's only a violation if it's vaginal
intercourse, not if it's anal intercourse. And the גמרא Gemara says הא
נמי כתיב, ha nami ksiv, what do you mean? That's also explicit
in the פסוק. pasuk. משכבי אשה, Mishkevei isha, the lyings of a
woman. And the plural comes to include, you know, both vaginal and
anal
again. say. If it's vaginal then even partial penetration. שלא כדרכה גמר
ביאה הוא דאסיר, shelo kedarka gmar bia hu de'asir, but if it's
anal intercourse then it's only full penetration. אבל העראה שריא. aval ha'ara
shraya. And that's not, that's not explicit in the verse. So the
גמרא Gemara says, "Wait a minute. אי הכי אפילו נדה? iy hachi
afilu Niddah? So then it's not a ruling about שומרת יום, Shomeres
Yom, about the woman of midcycle bleeding, it's a general ruling about
the forbidden sexual acts." Fine, let's go back to what we said
before. לעולם כדרכה. leolam kedarka. We're talking about vaginal penetration. ודאמרי העראה
באשה דווה הוא דכתיב. vedamri ha'ara be'isha dava hu dicsiv. They say
fine, but that פסוק pasuk that says משכבי אשה, mishkvei isha, that
partial penetration, that's only by a נדה. Niddah. But a woman who's
a זבה, Zava, it has to be full penetration. So we're still
back to this question of defining the act of intercourse, which is
not the simple sense of the משנה. Mishnah. But that for the
גמרא Gemara makes it feel that's enough not explicit in the verses
that the צדוקים Tzedukim wouldn't admit to that. ואיבעית אימא, ve'iba'is eima,
if you want I can tell you, דאמרי זבה לא הויא אלא
ביממי. de'amri Zava lo havya ela biyomami. Maybe here's what they say.
The case of a זבה Zava where it says bleeding in, you
know, in midcycle is only if she bleeds during the daytime, not
if she bleeds at night. דכתיב כל ימי זובה, dichsiv kol yemei
zova, the days. So they're actually, that's a דרשה drasha that you
could see how they're basing it on a פסוק. pasuk. And therefore
and therefore that's a position that would go against something, would not
go against a position that even the Sadducees would have said, because
that's not explicit in the verse. Okay? So that's how we got
that. I have to tell you personally, like I said before, it's
not so hard to read the verses to think that a woman
is only a זבה Zava if she bleeds two or three days
midcycle. But if she bleeds only one day, it's not clear in
the פסוקים psukim that she's actually a problem. So that actually would
be, I would imagine, something that would not go against a reading
of the Sadducees. But nevertheless the גמרא Gemara thinks that is explicit.
Okay, so now let's go on. תנן יש שבת פטורה אבל המוציא
מרשות לרשות פטור. tnan yesh Shabbas patura aval hamotzi me'reshus lireshus patur.
They deny there's something called carrying. So you could see how the
Sadducees might not disagree with that ruling, okay, because where does it
say in the Torah explicitly that you can't carry? So the גמרא
Gemara says, "Actually it does."
Why? In later prophets.
Ah, so that's what we're going to say. It doesn't say it
in the Torah but it says it in the נ"ך. Nach. Okay?
And that's interesting too that the Sadducees don't disagree with תנ"ך, Tanakh,
they just disagree with the Rabbinic tradition, but תנ"ך Tanakh presumably they
would use to interpret the Torah. ואיבעית אימא, ve'iba'is eima, I'm sorry,
so it says, ואמאי הוצאה כתיבא? ve'amai hotsaa ksiva? It says ולא
תוציאו משא מבתיכם. ve'lo sotsiu masa mibateichem. It says over by, I
think it's ירמיהו, Yirmiyahu, right? Where is that? Yeah, in ירמיהו: Yirmiyahu:
"Don't carry a burden from your houses." So that would be the
Sadducees would be clear that that, you know, that goes against a
reading that even the Sadducees agree on. So the גמרא Gemara says,
דאמרי הוצאה הוא דאסירא הכנסה שריא. de'amri hotsaa hu de'asira hachnasa shraya.
Fine, taking out of your houses is forbidden. Maybe bringing stuff from
the public domain into your house is permissible. ואיבעית אימא ve'iba'is eima
דאמרי הוצאה הוא דאסירא, de'amri hotsaa hu de'asira, maybe bringing in and
out of your house is forbidden, מושיט וזורק שרי, moshit vezorek shari,
but handing something through a window or throwing something out of the
house where you're not actually transporting it out, so maybe that's permissible.
So that's a and that's something that the Sadducees would not necessarily
disagree with. Okay. תנן יש עבודת כוכבים פטורה אבל משתחוה פטור. tnan
yesh avodas kochavim patura aval mishtachaveh patur. They say that bowing down
is forbidden. ואמאי, ve'amai, why according to your model would they, would
that be a ruling that they'd be חייב chayav for? Isn't that
something that the Sadducees would disagree? והא משתחוה הא כתיבא, ve'ha mishtachaveh
ha ksiva, bowing down is written, דכתיב לא תשתחוה לאל אחר. dichsiv
lo sishachaveh l'el acher. That's a pretty good point. There is a
pretty explicit פסוק. pasuk. All right, דאמרי כי אסירי השתחואה כדרכה אבל
שלא כדרכה שריא. de'amri ki asiri hishtachavaya kedarka aval shelo kedarka shraya.
We're back to the כדרכה. kedarka. Maybe that's only when it's the
normal way of this god to be worshipped by prostration. But if
it's a god like פעור Peor that's not normally worshipped this way,
maybe we, they would say you wouldn't be חייב. chayav. That's not
explicit in the פסוק. pasuk. ואיבעית אימא דמשתחויה גופא כדרכה הוא דאסירא,
ve'iba'is eima de'mishtachavaya gufa kedarka hu de'asira, even if that even when
you do השתחואה, hishtachavaya, what type of, what constitutes השתחואה? hishtachavaya? Maybe
they would say only normal השתחואה. hishtachavaya. דאית בה פישוט ידים ורגלים,
de'is bei pishut yadayim veraglayim, you both, you spread out your arms
and your legs. But השתחואה דלית בה פישוט ידים ורגלים, hishtachavaya de'leis
bei pishut yadayim veraglayim, let's say there's, you know, you're not doing
a full prostration, שרי, shari, maybe they'd say that's permissible. So there
are ways in which they could say that these things are permissible
and they and it would not go against a clear position of
the Sadducees. But if it would go against even something even the
Sadducees would say, then it's obviously wrong. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara says like this. בעי רב יוסף, ba'ei Rav Yosef, said רב
יוסף, Rav Yosef, אין חרישה בשבת מהו? ein charisha b'shabbos mahu? Now
we're moving on from the Sadducees model. We're getting back to this
question of a full ruling versus a partial ruling, a full body
of law versus
a
partial body of law. Let's say they get rid of one of
the מלאכות, melachos, okay? They say there are thirty-eight מלאכות, melachos, plowing
is not a problem. So is that considered they got rid of
a whole thing, of plowing, or is that a detail because it's
only one out of thirty-nine? Okay. מי אמרי כיון דקמודי בכולהו מילתא
כביטול מקצת וקיום מקצת דמי, Mi amri keivan d'kamodei b'kulhu milta k'bitul
miktar v'kiyum miktar damei, since they say the other thirty-eight apply,
so therefore they're only getting rid of a partial
thing? או דילמא כיון דעקרין ליה לחרישה כעקירה דגופא דמי, O dilma
keivan d'akrin leh l'charisha k'akira d'gufa damei, since they're completely getting rid
of this category of
plowing, כעקירה דגופא דמי, k'akira d'gufa damei, it constitutes a whole thing
and therefore they would be
exempt? תא שמע יש נדה בתורה אבל שומרת יום כנגד יום פטור.
Ta shema, yesh Nidda b'Torah aval Shomeret Yom k'Neged Yom patur. They're
getting rid of the—here they're getting rid of a category of שומרת
יום, Shomeret Yom, it's an entire part of the laws of נדה,
Nidda, and that's still considered a
detail. שומרת יום Shomeret Yom is certainly a different personal status than
נדה, Nidda, and nevertheless it's a detail. So if that's a detail,
certainly you should say one of the מלאכות melachos constitutes a detail
and not a whole
matter. ואמאי הא עקרין ליה לשומרת יום כנגד יום כעיקר? V'amai ha
akrin leh l'shomeret yom k'neged yom k'ikar? They're completely uprooting this category
called שומרת יום. Shomeret Yom. So you see that even a category
like that is considered to be not an entire
matter. אמר לך רב יוסף, Amar lach Rav Yosef, רב יוסף Rav
Yosef could say back, שומרת יום דאמרינן כדשנינן. Shomeret Yom d'amrinan k'deshaninan.
We already explained that the case of שומרת יום Shomeret Yom was
a detail within שומרת יום. Shomeret Yom. If you remember, it was
only days, it wasn't nights, it was the type of intercourse. The
way we had to explain it because of this idea of the
Sadducees, right, made us say that we're not talking about the whole
category of שומרת יום. Shomeret Yom. So that's—so you can't use that
as a proof to my question. תא שמע, Ta shema, let's try
again. יש שבת בתורה אבל הוצאה מרשות היחיד לרשות הרבים פטור. Yesh
Shabbos b'Torah aval hotza'ah mirishut hayachid lirishut harabim patur. Okay, you deny
הוצאה. hotza'ah. ואמאי הא עקרי להוצאה כעיקר? V'amai ha akrei l'hotza'ah k'ikar?
That is immediately parallel. You're trying to get rid of one of
the thirty-nine מלאכות, melachos, and it sounds like that's considered a detail,
not a whole
category. גמרא Gemara says, no, התם נמי כדשנינן. Hasam nami k'deshaninan. There
too, remember what we said? We said you're not trying to get
rid of all of הוצאה. hotza'ah. We said you're trying to say
going out is אסור, asur, taking in is permissible. So we tried
to—you know, we're talking about an aspect of הוצאה. hotza'ah. So that
doesn't answer my question where I'm trying to talk about a whole
מלאכה. melacha. תא שמע יש עבודת כוכבים בתורה אבל משתחוה פטור. Ta
shema, yesh avodat kochavim b'Torah aval mishtachaveh patur. Bowing down. ואמאי הא
עקרין משתחויה לעיקר? V'amai ha akrin mishtachavaya l'ikar? You're completely getting rid
of a category of
משתחויה. mishtachavaya. משתחויה נמי כדשנינן. Mishtachavaya nami k'deshaninan. No, we already just
answered that as well. We didn't totally get rid of משתחויה. mishtachavaya.
You got rid of it in a case of שלא כדרכה, shelo
kedarka, you got rid of it when it wasn't the way that
the god used to be worshipped that way, but you didn't get
rid of the whole category. So because of the ways we nuanced
all of the cases in the משנה, Mishna, we don't have an
answer to this question which is, if it's something that the Sadducees,
you know, don't agree upon, you know, and it's not—you know, and
it's a whole category, like it's something like you get rid of
a מלאכה melacha like חרישה. charisha. So the Sadducees might not say
that—although there it's a funny, he uses חרישה charisha because of all
the things it says, בחריש ובקציר תשבות. B'charish u-v'katzir tishbot. Okay, so
that might be talking about שמיטה, shmita, but nevertheless. Anyway, but let's
say it's a type of a thing that's not clear that the
Sadducees would disagree with, but it's still a whole category, like but
it's not the whole thing, it's one of the thirty-nine מלאכות. melachos.
Is that considered a detail or is that considered a whole thing?
And we don't have an answer because now all the things that
would have been relevant to that in the משנה, Mishna, we've nuanced
just to say we're not talking about the whole category, we're talking
about some detail within that category of bowing down, of הוצאה. hotza'ah.
Right,
exactly. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, תא שמע, Ta shema, I'm
sorry, so now we don't have an answer to that. Moving on
to the next question. בעי רב זירא, Ba'ay Rav Zeira, אין שבת
בשביעית מהו? Ein Shabbos b'Shevi'is mahu? Let's say they said שבת Shabbos
doesn't apply during a שביעית Shevi'is year. במאי טעו? B'mai ta'u? What,
how did they make—come to that mistake? בהדין קרא, B'hadayn kra, בחריש
ובקציר תשבות. B'charish u-v'katzir tishbot. Rest from plowing and from harvesting. בזמן
דאיכא חרישה איכא שבת ובזמן דליכא חרישה ליכא
שבת. Bizman d'ika charisha ika Shabbos u-v'zman d'leika charisha leika Shabbos. Maybe
שבת Shabbos only applies during a year where there are—where harvesting occurs,
where harvesting and plowing, but during a שביעית Shevi'is year where harvesting
and plowing don't occur, where, you know, tilling and plowing don't occur,
maybe there's no שבת. Shabbos. Okay, so that's an interesting read of
the פסוק. pasuk. Now, what's—okay, fine, so what—what's your question? Why shouldn't
they be
חייב? chayav? Right, it is a—right, so that's the question: is it
a detail, or if they say it doesn't apply at all for
a whole year, that's like a whole area? מי אמרינן כיון דמקיים
ליה בשאר שני שבוע כביטול מקצת וקיום מקצת דמי, Mi amrinan keivan
d'mikayim leh b'sha'ar shnei shavua k'bitul miktar v'kiyum miktar damei, since שבת
Shabbos applies according to them the six other years of the
cycle, then it's only a detail that they're sort of ruling
about? או דילמא כיון דעקרי ליה בשביעית כעקירת גופא דמי? O dilma
keivan d'akrei leh b'shevi'is k'akirat gufa damei? Since they're saying it doesn't
apply at all during שביעית, Shevi'is, it's like they completely got rid
of a whole category.
אמר רבינא תא שמע, Amar Ravina, ta shema, come here. נביא שנתנבא
לעקור דבר מדברי תורה חייב. Navi she-nitnaba l'akor davar m'divrei Torah chayav.
If a נביא Navi prophesies—here's a third category where we have the
idea, except here it's reversed, partial versus a complete area of law.
If a נביא Navi says—here it's funny because somebody is—it's—it's really interesting
to think about this. When somebody is talking with the authority of
a sage, they need the traction that they're de— dealing within a
body of law and getting a detail wrong. If they're coming to
reject the whole body of law, then they're like not even dealing,
it's, it's not even a legal act, okay, they're not, they don't
get that, the traction of that. But if somebody is coming as
a prophet, right, and as a false prophet, he is coming and
saying don't keep שבת *Shabas*, so there he, right, he's actually coming
with like not the authority of a sage, with the authority of
God's spokesman as it were. So you don't have to buy into
even a detail, and there it's more of a violation to be
rejecting a whole category, okay, because you're basically like, you understand conceptually
you're doing a very different thing when you're coming as a false
prophet as opposed to if you're coming as a זקן ממרא *zaken
mamre*.
Right, so נביא שנתנבא לעקור
דבר מדברי תורה חייב *navi she'nitnaba la'akor davar midivrei Torah chayav*. If
he's coming to completely get rid of it, he's חייב *chayav*. לבטלו
מקצת ולקיימו מקצת *levatlo mikzat u'lekaymo mikzat*, now let's say he's only
trying to get rid of a part of it, like saying don't
do X, Y, and Z on שבת *Shabas*, he's not saying it
doesn't apply. He's saying listen to me, I have a prophecy from
God, you're not supposed to do this on שבת *Shabas*. And part
of the challenge here is that sometimes נביאים *nevi'im* do tell people
to transgress, like when אליהו *Eliyahu* tells people to build the במה
*bamah* when there was a בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*. Okay, so what's
the story there? Sometimes there is a license to transgress a piece
of something. So רבי שמעון אומר פטור *Rabbi Shimon omer patur*, he's
exempt. Okay, so and but there's another position that he's חייב *chayav*.
So first of all that's fascinating, that he might be the mirror
image of the זקן ממרא *zaken mamre* is the נביא שקר *navi
sheker*. Their authority is coming from different places, and the זקן *zaken*
in an act of הוראה hora'ah, *hora'ah* means that you're within this
system. A נביא *navi* is sort of is coming from you know
just completely an opposite authority, you know an opposite divine authority.
But this was after the time of the prophets?
It doesn't matter, we're talking about, we're talking about what it would
have been. Okay, and therefore it's more radical and more out, you
know, when he's coming to get rid of the whole thing. Anyway,
ובעבודת כוכבים *u'be'avodat kochavim*, but when it comes to עבודה זרה *avoda
zara*, אפילו אמר היום עבדה ולמחר בטלה חייב *afilu amar hayom ovdah
u'lemachar bitlah chayav*. A נביא *navi* would be חייב *chayav* even according
to רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*, if he just said today worship עבודה
זרה *avoda zara* and not tomorrow. And it's based on a פסוק
*pasuk*, that there he thinks a נביא שקר *navi sheker* is חייב
*chayav* for even going against a part of something of a law,
and not a whole law. Okay, but you see that saying today
worship it and not tomorrow is considered to be going against a
part of a law and not a whole law. And presumably we're
going to use the same framework for our case as well. So
he's חייב *chayav*, so שמע מינה אין שבת בשביעית כביטול מקצת דמי
שמע מינה *shma mina ein Shabbat b'shvi'it k'bitul mikzat dami shma mina*.
So you see assuming that we're going to use the same definitions
and structures for נביא *navi* and זקן ממרא *zaken mamre* and for
הוראת בית דין *hora'as Beis Din* of the whole thing versus a
part thing, you see saying don't do it at this time and
do it at other times is considered to be only a part
of a thing, and therefore it, a בית דין *Beis Din* would
be חייב *chayav*. Okay, so that's the part number one. A בית
דין *Beis Din* is only חייב *chayav* and a נביא שקר *navi
sheker* and a זקן ממרא *zaken mamre*, well actually נביא שקר *navi
sheker* is the inverse, but a בית דין *Beis Din* and a
זקן ממרא *zaken mamre* are only חייב *chayav* only in an act
of הוראה hora'ah. *hora'ah* when it's a part of a thing and
not a whole thing getting wrong, and as was also mentioned, a
case that it's not צדוקים Tzaddukim מודים בו *Tzadukim modim bo*, so
there's enough sort of sense that the הוראה *hora'ah* was meaningful, it
wasn't going in the face of something obvious. Let's take a look
at the next משנה Mishnah *mishna*. הורו בית דין וידע אחד מהם
שטעו *horu Beis Din v'yada echad mehem she'tau*. This is going back
to, we quoted this earlier. What if one of them realizes they
made a mistake? So what we said was there's a position earlier
that you needed all of them to vote in the affirmative. The
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* rejected that, they don't all need to verbally consent,
but you know some people could maybe abstain or be silent. But
if one of them verbally tells them that they're wrong and dissents
and objects, then actually even though that's the normal rules of בית
דין *Beis Din*, you go by majority rule, once there's a dissenting
vote, it does not lead to the case of the בית דין
*Beis Din* bringing the קרבן *korban*. Okay, וידע אחד מהם שטעו *v'yada
echad mehem she'tau*, one knows they're making a mistake, ואמר להם טועין
אתם *v'amar lahem to'in atem*, you're making a mistake. או שלא היה
מופלא mufla שבבית דין שם *o she'lo haya mufla she'be'Beis Din sham*,
or another example, the sort of head of the court wasn't there.
Now the actual הלכה *halacha* is that if any member of the
court is missing, if you don't have a full quorum,
they're also פטור *patur*. But רש״י Rashi *Rashi* says the case here
would be that you had a full quorum, the, the head of
the court had to go somewhere and they appointed somebody to take
his place, like, you know, but or somebody to to fill up
the number, not to take his place. So there was the full
70 members of the court, but the head, but that's because somebody
had you know had the head had vacated his seat and somebody
filled the seat. Okay, so he's not there. או שהיה אחד מהם
גר ger, או ממזר mamzer, או נתין Netin, או זקן שלא ראוי
לבנים *o she'haya echad mehem ger o mamzer o natin o zaken
she'lo ra'uy l'banim*. So all these people are people that you know
can be on, can be on a בית דין *Beis Din* of
דיני ממונות *dinei mamonot* but can't be on a בית דין *Beis
Din* of דיני נפשות *dinei nefashot*, can't be on a capital case.
Now even though this is not a capital case, it's like a
ruling about forbidden fat, but since they're not considered to be at
the full level of a of הוראה *hora'ah*, the full level of
being able to have full judicial authority, then it's not considered to
be a, it's like they're absent as it were. and it's not
considered to be a full court, okay. נתין Netin is somebody of
a, it's like one of the, the people, the people who converted
at the time of יהושע, Yehoshua, you know, where they misrepresented themselves
and דוד David made them whatever water drawers. It's a whole question
about somebody with a bad sort of lineage, not fully Jewish, questionable
Jewish lineage, okay. So those first three, גר, ger ממזר, mamzer and
נתין, like גר is because it says like מקרב mikerev because it's
a position of authority. ממזר and נתין has to do with a
question of like some sense of genealogical purity that we want for
the court, which is a separate discussion. זקן שאין ראוי לבנים Zaken
she'ein ra'ui lebanim or שאין לו בנים she'ein lo banim is more
of a question, רש״י says I don't know why he's פסול pasul
as a judge. רמב״ם Rambam in פירוש המשניות Perush Hamishnayot says he's
פסול pasul because he doesn't have sufficient compassion. If he doesn't, he's,
you know, if he doesn't have any children of his own, then
maybe he doesn't, you know, I mean, it doesn't mean people can't
be compassionate, but it's maybe just a concern that they, you know,
so anyway, it's but it's fascinating that that scene is an exclusion.
הרי זה פטור, Harei zeh patur, then that's not a ruling of
the court, then the court is exempt. שנאמר כאן עדה ונאמר להלן
עדה, She'ne'emar kan edah vene'emar lehallan edah, it says here עדה edah
and it says elsewhere עדה, edah, which says with maybe says ושפטו
העדה. veshaftu ha'edah. מה עדה האמורה להלן, mah edah ha'amurah lehallan, I'm
not clear what the other להלן lehallan is. מה עדה האמורה להלן
כולן ראויין להוראה, Mah edah ha'amurah lehallan kullan ra'uyin lehora'ah, the same
way there it means that they're all fit to rule, אף עדה
האמורה כאן עד שיהיו כולן ראויין להוראה, af edah ha'amurah kan ad
sheyihyu kullan ra'uyin lehora'ah, which only gets to the last set of
cases, it doesn't get to the, to the idea of a person
objecting or the idea of the מופלא not being there. So the
גמרא Gemara. says, או שלא היה מופלא בית דין שם מנלן. o
shelo hayah mufla beit din sham menalan. So the issue about objecting
we had before was כל העדה, kol ha'edah, the entire congregation. So
even if you don't need them to all verbally assent, a verbal
dissent, you know, is what an oral dissent, right, is a, you
know,
would not be the sufficient criteria for obligation, okay. But how about
this other category that the head of the court has to be
there? אמר רב ששת וכן תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל נאמר אמרו הורו
בדבר שהצדוקים מודין בו פטורים, Amar Rav Sheshet vechen tana devei Rabbi
Yishmael ne'emar amru horu bedavar shehatzaddukim modin bo peturim, cause it's the
same idea, why when they, if they, if you, if they ruled
against something that even the צדוקים Tzaddukim disagree with are they exempt?
שהיה להם ללמוד ולא למדו, Shehayah lahem lilmod velo lamdu, because they
should have known better, they should have, it was so obvious, okay.
So לא היה מופלא שבבית דין שם נמי פטורים, Lo hayah mufla
shebeveit din sham nami peturim, the same reason if the head of
the court isn't there, they're exempt. שהיה להם ללמוד ולא למדו, Shehayah
lahem lilmod velo lamdu, because, you know, they should have known better,
they should have consulted with him. So, you know, so therefore it's
again, it's somehow they're not ruling with, you know, it's more like,
like an obvious mistake than it is like a, it doesn't have
enough traction as I was sort of saying to be called a
הוראה, a ruling, okay. Something that easily they could have found out
was, was wrong, you know, if they just would have like, you
know, checked. So therefore that's enough to sort of say it wasn't
a real ruling.
Now,
נאמר שם עדה ונאמר כאן עדה עד שיהיו כולן ראויין להוראה, Ne'emar
sham edah vene'emar kan edah ad sheyihyu kullan ra'uyin lehora'ah, והתם מנלן?
vehasam menalan? Where do you know in general that a court means
that they're like this idea of ראויין להוראה? ra'uyin lehora'ah? דאמר רב
חסדא אמר קרא והתיצבו שם עמך. De'amar Rav Chisda amar kra vehisyatzvu
sham immach. This is by משה Moshe when he gathers the 70
elders. So the funny thing is I don't think it really says
עדה edah there, but somehow we're sort of borrowing that concept, okay,
when the God spreads the spirit to the 70 elders. So therefore
it says עמך, immach, עמך בדומים לך, immach bidumim lach, they have
to be like you. So it's, that means that they have to
be of good lineage and all the types of things that are
implied in our משנה Mishnah. or stated in our משנה. Mishnah ואימא
עמך לשכינה? Ve'eima immach lashchinah? Maybe it just means with you so
that they could get the divine presence, you know, extend to them.
Maybe it doesn't mean that they have to be at the same,
have the same qualities as you do.
Also play on words, עמך immach and עמך. ammach.
אלא אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק אמר קרא ונשאו אתך, Ella amar
Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak amar kra venasu ittach, they'll carry with you
the burden of the people, אתך בדומים לך, ittach bidumim lach, like
you. So that's what we learned, some of these criteria of the
court, okay. But it is pretty fascinating that if the head of
the court isn't there, it's not considered like, I mean, it's not
so much like a procedural matter. Technically, it's not a legitimate ruling
because the head of the court wasn't present. It's more considered like
it's not a ruling that carries the same type of weight or
it's considered to be, I don't know, to me it feels different
than the צדוקים Tzaddukim thing. The צדוקים Tzaddukim seems like objectively off-base.
It's so objectively out of the, you know, you know, you know,
wrong, even the צדוקים know it's wrong, whereas here it's not objectively
wrong, it's just that you weren't operating with your full consideration, full
due consideration. And even that is enough to say it doesn't constitute
a real הוראה. Let's just read the next quick משנה and גמרא.
הורו בית דין שוגגין ועשו כל הקהל. Horu beit din shogegin ve'asu
kol hakkahal. You know what, let's not, okay. It's already 8:30 and
this needs a little bit more time. All right, we'll end here.